# 这一次主要是复习前面有两节
Today it's mostly a review of the two previous lessons.
# 有一节是麻婆豆腐
The one on Mapo Tofu.
# 还有一节是宝塔肉
And the pagoda meat.
# 宝塔肉就是关于勾芡这个问题
The problem about the sauce thickening.
# 昨天你师弟做了那个宝塔肉勾出来的芡
Yesterday, he made the gravy for the pagoda meat.
# 因为当时我不在现场
Because I wasn't there at the time.
# （汤汁）它是浑的
I saw it from video, the gravy is not clear.
# 所以我们
So we...
# 到底哪个是哪个粉哦
Which one is which starch powder?
# 我都搞不清楚了
I don't know what to use.
# 这个白的（土豆淀粉）来我们看一下
This white one (potato starch), let me show you.
# 你拿在手里面捏一下
Hold it in your hand and squeeze it.
# 听到没
Hear what I'm saying?
# 还有这个响声很响
That's a loud noise.
# 声音越响
The louder it gets.
# 就说明它越纯
The purer it is, the better.
# 你看看这个玉米淀粉
Look at this cornstarch.
# 虽然是也有
Although there also is...
# 也有那个响声
There's that noise too.
# 但是明显小很多声音而且不一样
But it's significantly quieter and the sound is different.
# 它更软更细
It's also softer and finer.
# 这个是红薯（淀）粉跟玉米淀粉混合的
This is a mixture of sweet potato starch and cornstarch.
# 这个就更不用说了 这个是
Not to mention this one, which is...
# 这个是什么淀粉哦
What kind of starch is this?
# 这个也是红薯淀粉
This is sweet potato starch.
# 它是没有经过精加工的
It's unrefined raw starch.
# 这种淀粉在四川拿来炸酥肉
This starch is used in Sichuan cuisine to fry meat.
# 用来码鱼是非常常见的
It's also very common to marinate fish.
# 还是说一下前面两个菜吧
Let's talk about those two dishes.
# 为什么麻婆豆腐要离火勾芡呢
Why Mapo tofu need to thicken the sauce off the fire?
# 之前学了复习一下
Revise what you learned before.
# 因为它的汤汁比较多
Because it's very soupy.
# 离火勾芡的话
If you thicken it off the heat
# 它那个汤汁不会浑
It's a thick sauce that doesn't get mushy.
# 应该就是这样子的吧
That's what I understand.
# 你都会抢答了
You've got the answer.
# 确实挺不错
It's pretty good.
# 但是把前面的忘记了
But you've forgotten the first reason.
# 豆腐离了火之后
After the tofu is off the fire
# 温度下降的时候它会出水
The water will come out from tofu when the temperature drops.
# 只有把水出出来然后再勾芡
You have to get the water out first and then thicken the sauce.
# 才勾得越紧
That's how you get a tighter sauce.
# 把豆腐包得越稳
Which will wrap the tofu as securely as possible
# 我们勾芡的时候带汤汁芡的时候
When we thicken the sauce with high amount of water...
# 菜一定要离火
Always remove the wok from the fire.
# 把它温度降下来
Let the temperature down a bit.
# 再去勾
Then thicken the sauce.
# （温度）稍微上到六七十度
After add the slurry then bring the temperature up to 60 or 70 °C.
# 七八十度它都会糊化
The starch slurry will thicken at 70 or 80 °C.
# 你勾得那个芡啊
The sauce you thickened.
# 第一是没勾均匀
First, it's not evenly distributed.
# 第二个是下锅的温度高了
Second, the temperature is too high.
# （温度）高了之后勾出来是浑的
When the wok is too hot, the sauce comes out muddy.
# 知道吧
You get it?
# 如果说是勾酱油芡
If we are making the soy sauce gravy.
# 不可以看起来是浑的
Muddy is not acceptable.
# 我们勾芡的芡粉
The starch slurry we thicken with.
# 勾得不够可以再加
You can add more if it's not enough.
# 对不对
Right?
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 你这样子淀粉放到水里面了
You put the starch in the water like this.
# 然后直接拌匀直接往锅里倒
Then mix it up and pour it directly into the wok.
# 一下子倒进去了
All in at once.
# 勾多了怎么办呢
What if you put too much starch in it?
# 勾多了这个汁是不是就报废了
If the sauce get too thick, it's a fail. (you can't do anything to save it)
# 所以我们勾芡要把它放到水里面
That's why we put the starch in water first.
# 这样拈起来三个指头
Pick it up with three fingers like this.
# 拈起来放到炒勺里面
Pick it up and put it in a frying spoon.
# 然后再加其它水
Then add more water to adjust it.
# 知道吧
You see?
# 都不能加这里面的水
You can't use the water from this.
# 这个你抓下面沉淀的东西
When you pick with your fingers, only pick the sediment from bottom.
# 抓起来是多少就是多少
It's a very controllable process.
# 不像你抓这个
It's not like you grab the dry starch.
# 有时候抓多一点有时候抓少一点
Sometimes a little more, sometimes a little less.
# 没有一个量
There is no controlled quantity.
# 你看我们用手法勾一下芡
You two see how I am handling it.
# 就是把它抓到里面
Pick the wet starch in.
# 看到没抓这种
Did you see?
# 嗯 抓这种
Pick it up.
# 然后呢
Then?
# 再里面加水
Add water to it.
# 把它稀释开来
Dilute it.
# 如果是玉米淀粉的话呢
What if it's cornstarch?
# 那就还要更浓
Then it has to be thicker.
# 因为玉米淀粉勾芡的效果
Because of the cornstarch thickening effect...
# 它吸水的效果不是很好
is not good as potato starch, it doesn't absorb water very well.
# 没有这个好
Not as good as this one.
# 所以就要加更多的淀粉来
So you have to add more starch to it.
# 这个可不可以勾芡
Can I thicken the sauce with this?
# 这个也可以勾芡
This can also be thickener.
# 但是勾的芡出来是灰色的
But the sauce will come out a bit grey.
# 因为你看
Because you see...
# 本身就带颜色
It got color in it.
# 是吧
Right?
# 所以我讲了勾芡
That's why I told you when choose thickening starch.
# 那最好是无色的
It better be colorless.
# 越白越好
The whiter, the better.
# 待会儿你们用
You can try them later.
# 在锅里面放一点水
Put a bit water in the wok.
# 放一点酱油来模拟
Pour some soy sauce in to simulate it.
# 你把这个淀粉按照我刚刚说了这个来勾
Thicken the sauce just like what I taught you.
# 烧开了之后锅离火
Remove the wok from the heat after boiling.
# 让它水温降下去
Let the water cool down a bit.
# 然后这个再放下去
And then add the slurry in.
# 搅它几下 让它均匀了
Give it a few stirs to even it out.
# 然后再下锅去烧一下
Then go back to the fire and thicken it.
# 好 那我们先试一下吧
Well, let's try it.
# 今天课就先上到这里
That's enough lessens for today.